Curriculum Vitae

Julien COLOMB, PhD in Biology Schillerpromenade 4 12049 Berlin julien.colomb@fu-berlin.de

https://github.com/jcolomb http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520

Birth: 9 April 1979 in Sion (CH) Married, two children Swiss



Summary

After 12 years spent on fundamental research (neuro-genetics) in which I gathered skills in experimental design, team leading and student teaching, I got most interested in open science and research reproducibility as well as the digital tools helping scientists to achieve it. I would like to apply these novel knowledge while doing research and mentoring students.

Commercial activities

2016-present Freelance scientist,

Animal core facility (Charité): organisation lead, data analysis in R

Phenobase (Exist, HU): literature curation.

2012-present Founder and CEO of Drososhare GmbH (Berlin, Germany),

a company developing an automated fly transaction system.

Non-commercial activities

2015- present Organisation of the Berlin Open Science meetup:

- Discussion and brainstorming on open science themes (Reproducible Research,

Open Access, peer review)

- Organisation of the open con satellite

Non-commercial activities

2015- present Part of the march for science Berlin Orga team:

we organised a protest in 2017 (11000 people) and are using this momentum to make bridges between science and society

Research activities

2017 - present Postdoctoral fellow, HU (**Berlin**, Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter

Analysing mulitdimensional dataset: the homecagescan case.

2015 - 2016	Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charité (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
2014 2015	Animal core facility director and project manager. Postdoctoral follows HIL & Charita (Porlin Commany) by Prof. V. Winter
2014 - 2015	Postdoctoral fellow, HU & Charite (Berlin , Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter
0000 0010	working on Phenobase.
2009 -2013	Postdoctoral fellow, FU (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. B. Brembs
2007-2008	working on "the what and where of operant learning in <i>Drosophila</i> ". Postdoctoral fellow, ESPCI (Paris , France), by Dr. T. Preat
	working on "appetitive learning in <i>Drosophila</i> ".

Education

2016	FELASA B. HU Berlin
2013	Moderation & management (Continuing Education), FU Berlin/Artop.
2006	PhD in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg, Switzerland).
	PhD dissertation: "The chemosensory system of Drosophila larvae: neu-
	roanatomy and behaviour" Thesis director: Prof. R.F Stocker
2002	Diploma in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg, Switzerland)
1998	"Maturité fédérale type C" (scientific subsection), in the "Collège de la royale
	Abbaye de St. Maurice"

Languages

French (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (fluent), Spanish (basics).

$Research\ output$

 $\rm https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520$

8 research papers (7 first author), 3 reviews, 1 Scienceopen collection

https://github.com/jcolomb

3 Open source software (2 main author) h-index =7, Meeting Presentations = 25

$Supervision\ of\ student$

2010-2014	Co-supervisor of the PhD student Christine Damrau (with Dr. B.Brembs) on
2008	the role of octopamine in reward, motivation and motor control in <i>Drosophila</i> . Co-supervisor of the PhD student Séverine Trannoy (with Dr. G. Isabel and
	Dr. N. Gervasi) on the role of dopamine in appetitive learning consolidation in
	Drosophila.
2005	Co-supervisor of the diploma work of Claire Huguenin (with Dr. A. Ramaekers)
	on the role of NO in olfactory discrimination in <i>Drosophila</i> larvae.

Teaching experience

2016	Animal models of neuropathy, (master student, 2x2h lecture, organisation)
2012	Genetik (bachelor student, 2 x 3 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2012	Neurogenetik. (master student, 2 x 2 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2011	Practical course neurobiology. (7 x 4 h., Practical course supervision)
2011	Entwicklung der Insekten [Insect development] (2 h. lecture)
2006	Fluorescence and Confocal Microscopy (master student, 3h. lecture)
2003-2006	Studying behavior. (master student, 2 h. lecture)
2003-2005	Developmental- and Neurogenetics (master student, 2 h. lecture).

$Computer\ skills$

Organisation: Outlook, Access Publishing: \LaTeX , Office; html; Image processing: Photoshop,

Illustrator, Image J;

Programming: R (advanced), Git, Labview

Other tasks

Creation of the T. Preat's and R.F. Stocker's lab website. Co-director in the theater group "les apostrophes" in 2006

RESEARCH PRODUCTS

Open source Software

- (2011-2013) CeTrAn 1.4 to 4.0, developed on Github (https://github.com/jcolomb/CeTrAn). Used for more than three research papers.
- (2016) Viewer data concatenator (shiny app).
- (2013-2016) Collaborating on Rfigshare and Rflybase (https://github.com/ropensci/rfigshare).

Peer review publications

Five most important publications:

- (2016). **Julien Colomb** and Björn Brembs.

 " PKC in motorneurons underlies self-learning, a form of motor learning in Drosophila" PeerJ (e1971).

 cited 3 times
- (2014). **Julien Colomb** and Björn Brembs. "Sub-strains of Drosophila Canton-S differ markedly in their locomotor behavior". F1000RESEARCH (3:176). cited 15 times
- (2009). **Julien Colomb**, Laure Kaiser, Marie-Ange Chabaud, Thomas Preat. "Parametric and genetic analysis of Drosophila appetitive long-term memory and sugar motivation" Genes Brain and Behaviour (8 (4): 407-415). cited 52 times
- (2007). **Julien Colomb**, Nicola Grillenzoni, Ariane Ramaekers, and Reinhard F. Stocker. "Architecture of the primary taste center of *Drosophila melanogaster* larvae". J. comp. neurol. (502: 834-847). cited 72 times
- (2007). **Julien Colomb**, Nicola Grillenzoni, Reinhard F. Stocker, and Ariane Ramaekers. "Complex behavioural changes after odour exposure in *Drosophila* larva". Anim. Behav. (73 (4): 579-85). cited 13 times

Other Publications

• (In revision). Christine Damrau, Naoko Toshima, Teiichi Tanimura, Björn Brembs Julien Colomb.

- "Octopamine and Tyramine contribute separately to the counter-regulatory response to sugar deficit in Drosophila." Frontiers
- (2014). Ezequiel Mendoza, **Julien Colomb**, Jürgen Rybak, Hans-Joachim Pflüger, Troy Zars, Constance Scharff, and Björn Brembs.
 - "Drosophila FoxP mutants are deficient in operant self-learning". Plos One (9(6): e100648). cited 15 times
- (2012). **Julien Colomb**, Lutz Reiter, Jedrzej Blaszkiewicz, Jan Wessnitzer and Björn Brembs.
 - "Open Source Tracking and Analysis of Adult Drosophila Locomotion in Buridan's Paradigm with and without Visual Targets." Plos One (7(8): e42247). cited 34 times
- $\bullet \,$ (2010). Julien Colomb, Björn Brembs
 - "biology of psychology: "simple conditioning" "Communicative and Integrative Biology (3 $(2)\colon 142\text{-}145).$

cited 20 times

- (2008). Julien Colomb
 - "Discriminative learning, learning generalization and masking tests as three strategies to assess olfactory discrimination." Animal Behaviour: New Research 185-192 cited 0 times
- (2007). **Julien Colomb***, Rüdiger Bader*, Bettina Pankratz, Anne Schröck, Reinhard F. Stocker, and Michael J. Pankratz.
 - "Genetic dissection of a neural circuit underlying feeding behavior in *Drosophila*: distinct morphology of single *hugin* expressing neurons". J. comp. neurol. (502: 848-856).
 - * the two authors participated equally to this work. cited 67 times
- (2007). Julien Colomb, Reinhard F. Stocker
 - "Combined rather than separate pathway for hedonic and sensory aspects of taste in Drosophila larvae." FLY (1 (4): 232-234). cited 5 times

Meeting presentations (4 most representative)

- 2016 Faster and more reproducible science: Open Science. ORAL PRESENTATION at the neurofly meeting, Creta, Greece.
- 2008 New insight into appetitive Long term memory in *Drosophila*. POSTER PRESENTATION at the FENS Forum, Geneva, Switzerland.
- 2006 Sub-regions in the primary taste center of *Drosophila* larvae. ORAL PRESENTATION at the 11th European Drosophila neurobiology Conference, Leuven, Belgium
 - Learning by odor exposure in agar plate. ORAL PRESENTATION at the behavioural neurobiology of *Drosophila* larvae meeting, Würzburg, Germany.

2002 Functional studies of the chemosensory system of the Drosophila larva using a new tool: the GAL4 / UAS-shi ts system. ORAL PRESENTATION at the Swiss Drosophila meeting, Basel, Switzerland.